Guide to the Charles Lamb Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Charles Lamb collection
1798-1835
GEN MSS 254
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.4
(4 boxes)
Correspondence and writings by or relating to Charles Lamb. The correspondence includes letters to Edward Moxon, Basil Montagu, and William Wordsworth. The writings includes an autograph manuscript of "Elia to his Correspondents," and a sonnet, beginning "They talk of time, and of time's galling yoke...." Accompanying material includes a pamphlet on Lamb by Edward Moxon, no. 703 of The Mirror, and two engraved portraits of Lamb.
Lamb, Charles, 1775-1834
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Charles Lamb, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Materials given by Cornelia Cogswell Sage have been organized into the first series. Materials added to the collection by gift and by purchase from various sources are located in Series II.
Authors, English -- Archives; Lamb, Charles, 1775-1834; Montagu, Basil, 1770-1851; Moxon, Edward, 1801-1858; Wordsworth, William, 1770-1850
- Gift of Cornelia Cogswell Sage, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Given in memory of Henry Manning Sage,
  Yale 1890, by his wife Cornelia Cogswell
  Sage, 1954.
  - Correspondence
    - AL to Charles Cowden Clarke, no place, [1828 Dec]
      Paper watermarked 1819. Bound with
      Letters to Mrs. Williams and Southey
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Oversize, box 2, folder 21
    - AL to Edward Moxon, [1831 Aug]
      Signed 'Peter.' Bound with "On Some
      of the Old Actors," and "Elia to his
      Correspondents"
      See: Oversize, box 3, folder 22
    - ALS to Robert Southey, no place, [1798 Dec 27]
    - 2 ALS to Mrs. Williams, Enfield, 1830 Mar 1, 5
      Concerning Lamb's adopted daughter
      Emma Isola, later Mrs. Edward Moxon,
  - Writings
    - "Elia to his Correspondents," autograph ms.
      Signed 'Elia'
    - "On Some of the Old Actors," autograph ms.
- Additional Materials, Series II
  Other materials acquired from various
  sources
  - Correspondence
    - ALS to Frances Brown, no place, n.d.
      Gift, 1970
      See: Oversize, broadside, folder 23
    - ALS to "H." [James Augustus Hessey of Messrs. Taylor and Hessey], London, [1824 Oct 8]
      Offering a letter of James Thomson
      for publication. Accompanied by the
      galley proof of Thomson's letter with
      ms. corrections and a note to Hessey
      on verso in the hand of Charles Lamb.
      Attached to top of galley sheet is
      the introductory note (written in an
      unidentified hand) used when
      Thomson's letter was printed in the
      "London Magazine," November 1824
      Purchase, 1950
      See: Oversize, broadside, folder 24
    - ANS to Hessey, of Messrs. Taylor and Hessey, London (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Gift, 1933
    - ALS to William Hone, no place, 1827 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ALS to Thomas Hood, [Enfield], [1828 May] (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Gift, 1956
    - AN to the editors of the London Magazine (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Mentioning Elia. Removed from his
      John Woodvil, London, 1802
      Purchase, 1947
    - ALS to Basil Montagu, no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Lamb writes that William Hazlitt is
      "lying in bed as bad as man can be
      that is alive"
      Purchase, 1954
    - ALS to [Charles] Ollier, no place, [1826 May 12] (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Accompanied by a typewritten copy
      Purchase, 1946
    - AL to Peter George Patmore, 1831 Apr 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Gift, 1965
    - AL (fragment) to John Howard Payne, [1823 Jan 6] (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Gift, 1974
    - ALS to Samuel Rogers, Enfield, 1824 Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Accompanied by a sonnet, "To Mrs. S.
      Rogers of the Death of his Brother,"
      a manuscript in an unidentified
      hand
    - ALS to John Taylor, no place, [1822?] (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Gift, 1954
    - ALS to William Wordsworth, no place, [1824?] (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
      Mentions William Harrison Ainsworth,
      Samuel Taylor Coleridge, and George
      Dyer. Paper watermarked 1823.
      Ainsworth arrived in London in 1824.
      With case carrying bookplate of
      Moncure Biddle Purchase, 1961
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, [London], [1821] (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Letter begins, "Dear H..."
    - ALS from Charles Ryle to Francis John Field [E.I. House], [1834]
      Telling him of the death of Charles
      Lamb
      Gift, 1941
      See: Oversize, box 4, folder 25
  - Writings
    - Lamb, Charles. "In tabulam eximii pictoris B. Haydoni, in quâ Solymoei adveniente Domino," holograph, n.d.
    - Lamb, Charles. Original manuscripts. "In tabulam eximii pictoris B. Haydoni, in quâ Solymoei adveniente Domino," "Translation of the Latin verses on Mr. Haydon's picture" and "The three graves"
      Presented to Francis John Field by
      Edward Moxon, with the portrait here
      placed as a frontispiece, and the
      letter from Ryle to Field bound in.
      "The three graves" is written on the
      verso of "The translation."
      The paper is water-marked 1818.
      The binding is full brown crushed
      levant morocco, gilt and blind tooled,
      with doublures and end leaves of green
      watered silk, gilt edges.
    - Lamb, Charles. Sonnet, autograph manuscript, signed with initials, 1820 Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Sonnet begins: "They talk of time,
      and of time's galling yoke..." On
      verso, in pencil: "Endorsed by D. C.
      Higg." Accompanied by a note from
      Dodd, Mead & Co. concerning the
      authenticity of the manuscript.
    - Lamb, Charles. "The three graves," holograph, n.d.
    - Lamb, Charles. "Translation of the Latin verses on Mr. Haydon's picture" holograph, n.d.
    - Moxon, Edward. "Charles Lamb," autograph manuscript signed, with initials, 1835 Jan 27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Papers from Original Manuscripts Vol.
      Full heading: Papers from the Pocket
      of the Original Manuscripts Volume
      - Photostat of letter from Charles Ryle to Francis John Field, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Original is in box 4, folder 25
      - Two engraved portraits of Charles Lamb, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
        In a paper wrapper addressed to "F.
        Field, Esq. India House" and
        inscribed in the upper left corner,
        "Portrait with autograph verses --
        Charles Lamb", and in the lower left
        corner, "With Mr. Moxon's
        Compliments."
      - Charles Lamb, printed pamphlet signed E. M. [Edward Moxon], 1835 Jan 27 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - The Mirror no. 703, 1835 Jan 24 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Pages 135-136 from an unidentified publication, containing a tribute to Lamb, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Oversize, [1828 Dec]
  - AL to Charles Cowden Clarke, no place (from Series I), [1828 Dec] (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - AL to Edward Moxon (from Series I), [1831 Aug] (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - ALS to Frances Brown, no place (from Series II), n.d. (Box bsd, folder 23)
  - ALS to "H." [James Augustus Hessey of Messrs. Taylor and Hessey], London (from Series II), [1824 Oct 8] (Box bsd, folder 24)
    - Lamb, Charles. Original manuscripts. "In tabulam eximii pictoris B. Haydoni, in quâ Solymoei adveniente Domino," "Translation of the Latin verses on Mr. Haydon's picture" and "The three graves" (Box 4, Folder 25)
      Edward Moxon, with the portrait
      here placed as a frontispiece, and
      the letter from Ryle to Field bound
      in. "The three graves" is written
      on the verso of "The translation."
      levant morocco, gilt and blind
      tooled, with doublures and end
      leaves of green watered silk, gilt
      edges.